hello and thank you for joining us for
today's discussion on the insurance
industry i'm kevin orland and i cover
canadian banks and insurers for
bloomberg news with me today are lee
chalmers senior vice president head of
corporate finance and capital management
for sun life financial and helena
vondemhagen global treasurer and head of
capital management for manulife
financial welcome to you both
so at the start of the summer
it looked like the accelerating
vaccination programs would have allowed
a full reopening of the economy by now
however vaccine resistance and the
spread of the delta variant have
prevented that so how is the prolonged
nature of the pandemic affecting your
businesses we'll start with lee on that
one
well thanks kevin and and thanks for
having me it's great to be back it's uh
it's hard to believe it's been a year
since we had this conversation and uh
who would have thought we'd still be
working from home 18 months later so
it's great to be here and uh you know
it's great to see helena again i guess
you know what i wanted to do was talk a
little bit about sort of
how our business has you know
been impacted by cobit so sort of going
back to the beginning and really touch
upon a few aspects of it you know
starting with our clients
maybe touched a little bit upon digital
and how that's really changed our
business um looking at the performance
of our business and then lastly on our
people because obviously we've all
switched had a big shift as we we've
been adjusting to this pandemic so maybe
starting with the clients obviously
clients are the center of our strategy
everything we do is revolves around the
client thinking about how do we serve
our clients so you know as we entered
into this pandemic
you know we are already shifting to
using more digital tools but the
adoption rate wasn't really there right
people weren't really willing to go out
and talk to their advisors um remotely
virtually so we continued to see a big
shift um and being able to access our
clients um and
you know having that open dialogue with
between our clients and our advisors so
i'd say that's been a big change
um you know the other part of it you
know what as we pivoted with the
pandemic it was really about getting the
right products and services to our
clients um you know we introduced
automatic underwriting which allowed us
to continue with underwriting policies
without having the lab work so i think
there was great traction there the
industry as a whole moved more to
e-signatures
and i think the real push we did was
around you know those partnerships and
you know introducing virtual care so
making sure that our clients could
continue to get the care they needed and
i have to say you know 18 months in i'm
shocked at how many times you know we've
been online connecting with the doctors
you know my kids have
to meet their doctor so we're always
online and it's now really become part
of sort of that regular health care and
how we interact with our doctor so i'd
say from a client perspective we really
pivoted and that continues and i'd say
overall the pandemic has really enforced
reinforced our purpose so helping our
clients access the care they need so i
think that's really sort of shown
throughout the entire pandemic that
we've been dealing with
on the digital front i wanted to touch
upon was really about
again we had the digital tools rolled
out we've certainly continued to see the
acceleration of
you know our advisors being enabled by
digital tools you know as we've gone
through lockdowns obviously it's gone
through series of waves you know across
all our geographies we operate in and um
the ability to access our clients
remotely has allowed us to continue to
push through those sales and and access
our clients and continue the funnel and
the pipeline of our business so i think
that's been excellent
um i would say as an organization you
know we're really focused on uh
everything digital so we refer to it as
the digital enterprise and i'd say the
pandemic has allowed us to continue to
accelerate that we're investing in our
tech stock stack
we're continuing looking at our client
journey so i'd say more than ever
it's
really important to make sure our
clients are able to access easily access
and processing their claims is easily
pushing through our applications so i'd
say from a digital side we continue to
see
um you know significant acceleration and
maybe just a couple proof points you
know in canada we have our digital coach
ella and ella has connected you know
more than with you members more than 3.4
million times um you know how we're
seeing that flow through in our results
is you know we're seeing increased
wealth deposits you know just year to
date you know at q2 you know we're at
over 400 million in additional deposits
as a result of those digital connections
same with insurance coverages over 600
million um and then i'd say in the us um
you know we invested in a company
maxwell health and that was a digital
benefits platform and as a result
through 2020
every single one of our digital our
enrollments were done virtually so a
real success and i think if anything the
virtual enrollments demonstrated the
value
um of that tool and allowed us actually
to accelerate sales because of that
uh and then in asia i'd say the same
thing
all right so uh yeah i'll continue so
okay so so yeah so i think those are the
key points you know i didn't want to
touch upon you know so the impact on our
business and but maybe before maybe why
don't i turn it to helena she can touch
upon it and then i can come back and
maybe touch upon a few other things i
don't want to take up all the time
yeah so helena how how has the the sort
of prolonged nature of the the pandemic
been affecting manulife
so so manulife and the industry in
general if i may so i i think insurance
companies in general proved quite
resilient
both operationally and from a business
perspective and
a lot had to do with the digital tools
that we had at our disposal and we
already put them in place prior to the
pandemic but very similar to some life's
experience the adoption rates were not
as
strong
as we would uh like prior to the
pandemic of course the lockdowns
restrictions on physical distancing
necessitated uh
like the adoption of those tools and we
were very happy to see it and we believe
that this trend will continue like for
example in canada and asia 97
of our annualized premium equivalence is
accessible to customers through the
non-uh face-to-face solutions we also
have capabilities to accept digital
claim submissions we enhance throughout
2020 our straight through uh processing
and just like to prove like some again
points regarding the digitization
in the us uh 100 of the insurance
contracts were delivered digitally at
the end of 2020 compared to 20 percent
before the pandemic so so a very rapid
increase and in canada the comparable
numbers uh stood at 60
for the electronic delivery of insurance
contracts in q4 2020 relative to 40
prior to the pandemic so a rapid
increase so i would say like when you
think insurance and kovid 19 maybe the
first
adjective that should come to mind is is
resilience and the same was true about
our staff
literally overnight and with no hiccups
we moved to working from home
for manulife over 95 of our global
workforce of over 37 000 staff
including asia has worked from home at
some point during the pandemic and
currently 98 of our north american staff
continues to to work from home so this
resilience combined with uh the fact
that pandemic also increased awareness
uh of of benefits of protection
explains also our business results
i think in case of manulife another
adjective that's critical is diversified
diverse uh we have a
lot
of diversification of our businesses
we are present in canada us and in asia
we are one of three pan-asian insurance
companies we operate in a very
meaningful way in 13 markets across asia
asia
already
contributes one-third to core earnings
of manulife and we are also diversified
between insurance and global wealth and
asset management that contributes one
quarter to our earnings so so and within
um global wealth and asset management
there is a diversification of lines
between
retirement retail and institutional so
this diversification again greatly
greatly contributed to the
strong business results uh we reported
5.9 billion net income um in 2020 the
year to date results first half of 2021
st stays at stands at 3.4 billion so so
i would say a very resilient and
impressive uh
performance um from from the insurance
industry broadly of course including
including manulife my my own company i
also if i may wanted to comment because
on on on risks that
were feared but didn't materialize so i
think there was a lot of anxiety when
the pandemic uh uh
struck regarding our business and and
the insurance claims uh what was not
appreciated enough and came through very
strongly is diversif diversification
within our insurance risks between
mortality and longevity for example
similarly between
certain business lines such as travel
insurance and other business lines such
as dental claims etc like that sort of
uh attempt to offset uh
the impacts on on the bottom line
through throughout the pandemic so
the and and in general i don't think it
was appreciated how how well the
mortality risk is managed within
insurance
how
we use their insurance risk mitigation
tools to to to make to keep it under
control so these risks pertaining to you
know pandemic
health death life insurance companies
problems this did not materialize at all
i would say and similarly there was a
lot of anxiety at the beginning of the
pandemic pertaining to credit risk
and again
arguably partly through the support and
action of central banks and access to to
credit etc but also in general i think
disciplined approach in the books of of
manulife for sure
and insurers maybe more generally we
didn't
see like widespread defaults that would
hit the bottom line of of insurance
companies
instead like some some other concerns
emerged like most notably uh concerning
commercial real estate market office and
shopping malls and similar so i just
found it interesting how
our perceptions at the onset of the
pandemic were sort of modified by by
by the events as as they uh
unfold
thank you so hello
helena brings up an interesting point
which is that uh you know the pandemic
really
sort of altered a lot of the typical
insurance claims and usage trends that
um you know people had seen previously
and also probably would have expected uh
these things changed in ways that people
wouldn't have expected during the
pandemic so i was wondering if you could
talk just a little bit about how
sunlight saw those uh
claims and usage trends changed during
the pandemic and is there any sign that
some of those trends are returning back
to normal or have some of them been
permanently altered
yeah no and i think that's a great
question and i mean helena touched a lot
upon you know and about the benefits of
the diversification of our businesses so
you know i'd say sun life is the same
and i'd say not only it's about the
diversification by products but it's
also the geographic diversification so
when the pandemic hit you know it hit in
asia and we sort of thought great we're
a global company it's just impacting our
asia business but then you know as it
came to become a global pandemic
obviously you know our entire businesses
were impacted but impacted at different
times so i think because of that
diversification we were managed to sort
of weather through the storm and and so
you know like helena said sort of how
our businesses interacted
really allowed us to continue to perform
and produce strong results so in terms
of trends we saw around insurance
experience you know you know i'd sort of
start maybe with our us business where
we have a stop-loss business that
because less people are using their
benefits we've had very very strong
performance we also have a group life
business that of course are are having
some implications as a result of
mortality claims coming through but
overall a strong result on our u.s
business so you're seeing that
diversification i'd say in your trends
we're continuing to see
you know we're you know us unfortunately
varies state by state varies depending
on the level of vaccination rates so
again we're seeing diversification
across states but we are seeing still
lower usage around our stop-loss
business and and we continue to see
particularly in q2 we continue to see
some um life mortality claims coming
through unfortunately turning to canada
i would say
you know again we didn't ever see
significantly high mortality claims
coming through again that goes to the
risk mitigation we have in place whether
it's the risk selection at the outset of
who we're insuring or also the use of
reinsurance as helena had mentioned so
not being impacted significantly by life
claims uh we did see a lower usage of um
dental and health benefits we are seeing
that start to return back to sort of
normalized pre-pandemic levels uh and
then on ltd claims you know obviously
that's something we're continuing to
manage and monitor
and so maybe going to our last geography
in asia is uh unfortunately you know
with where they are in the in the
pandemic we you know in q2 by the end of
q2 we're seeing some geographies you
know china and hong kong starting to
introduce lockdowns again you know
vietnam was a country who fared very
well
um through the process and now
unfortunately they're in lockdown and so
we're seeing some implication of
headwinds coming through on our bank
assurance sales
as a result of the banks being closed so
again various geography by geography but
um seeing some positive signs and
unfortunately some countries still sort
of weathering through
the pandemic
okay so now over the past year we've
also seen interest rates rise uh they're
they're off their lows of the pandemic
but they they are down from where they
were at you know the sort of the start
of this year
so i'm curious how those moves and some
of the fluctuations we've seen in the
yield curve affected your company's
financing strategy let's start with
helena on that one
so um i have to say like generally like
so so uh we when we entered the pandemic
we entered with a strong capital levels
and strong liquidity and very high
quality asset portfolios and i think
this is true
across the industry however like the
volatile markets that ensued and
especially like the first few months of
of the pandemic when when i described
that the markets in many ways like lost
their identity and and there was a great
uncertainty uh with respect to
the economic
developments and the central banks
response etc it greatly affected my
thinking horizon when it comes to
pre-financing actions like normally we
never like to be squeezed into the
markets so i i i say like one
transaction ahead of
of the markets meaning like you go where
you don't quite yet need it but just to
to to optimize uh the size and and the
price
but i like we started thinking in in the
categories of like up to 12 months of
pre-financing so a macro uncertainty
certainly made this approach prudent and
historically low costs made it very uh
affordable uh in in in fact like this
allowed us to also choose the markets
that we want to access manulife greatly
diversified its
funding sources we are now very well
established in four markets
in canada in the united states in
singapore and in formosa taiwan uh uh
through those two asian markets we have
access to the asian investor base and uh
provide alignment with with our presence
in on on the continent there so during
the 2020 and 21 to date
we issued 6.3 billion
in various markets and various
instruments we also redeemed close to
4.5 billion so so it wasn't only like on
a net basis and given like the preceding
years where we largely
leveraged we are almost like net
but uh still it's it's been a very busy
time to to the treasury um and and uh
the communication to stakeholders
including rating agencies uh was
critical throughout because
of the timing difference between the
issuance and this
subsequent redemption
that created spikes in the leverage
ratio for example
we
issued in the formosa market over 1
billion u.s in 40-year senior debt
in september of 2020 but redeemed 1
billion in june of 2021 at 165
beeps cheaper our issue like the on the
net basis our our issuance was relative
to
redemption saving us 12 million dollars
in in interest rate expenses uh annually
uh in general uh our net awaited cost of
debt
since 2016 decreased by almost 100 basis
points which is like a
a very high number some of it is of
course the natural
decrease in risk free rates that we
experienced
and spread straightening etc but it's
also like sort of you know this being on
the ball uh um
taking advantage of how various markets
uh opened uh in different times with uh
with cost advantage
really allowed to to
benefit from from those opportunities i
also have to say that throughout 2020
the canadian market home market
was very attractive
and this was uh apparent not only to us
but also to to foreign issuers uh that
came to to the canadian market
uh so so all together
notwithstanding the uncertainties uh
once like you adopt this uh
proactive approach and sort of look for
opportunities ahead of needs
um it has been a busy but quite an
orderly uh process i would say
right now where i stand
there is still a great deal
of uncertainty not so much as a year ago
because
now we have a track record of the
coordinated determined response from
central banks that support the numbers
but of the markets but i still would
think it's a prudent
to sort of think very proactively about
the financing needs
okay
and then lee how has sun life's
financing strategy uh
been in response to those interest rate
changes and what do you uh what is the
company's strategy looking forward to
yeah i guess i would say you know
similar to what helena said i mean we've
never been you know we've been in a low
interest rate environment for a long
time so it certainly wasn't the low
interest rate environment that would
cause us to go out and do additional
financing or pre-fi pre-funding uh but
but like helena said when the pandemic
hit we really looked at the opportunity
to look farther out so what was you know
what were those
uh pre what for the next 12 months what
would we want to pre-finance so we also
took you know looked at the market and
took advantage of those so those low
rates so again did a 1 billion issuance
in may of 2020 followed that in in 2020
with another 750 million some of that
being pre-financing and some of it just
opportunistically taking advantage of
the market and maybe just one thing to
add is uh you know is i think manulife
took advantage of it as well but the new
lrcn
instruments that were issued
that gave us an opportunity to look at
sort of our capital structure and reduce
our capital funding and and we launched
an lrcn of 1 billion in june which
allowed us again to save you know
approximately 9 million a year in
financing costs so real opportunity to
look at our structure and again we'll
continue to do that uh as we move
forward and manage and monitor the the
capital markets and and the pandemic
all right and then just uh briefly i
know um you know both your companies
have been active in this space but what
uh we've seen the global um green bond
market and sustainable financing really
move up uh companies priority lists um i
was just wondering if you could talk a
little bit about how your company is
approaching the sustainable finance
start with lee on that one
yeah so so you know obviously we
launched our sustainability bond
framework now a couple years ago and
issued a sustainable bond right after i
think that's something that continues to
be a priority i mean for us esg
is a real focus for our investment uh
investing portfolio
we've come out and said that we're
committed to an additional 20 billion in
sustainable investments within five
years
um so that's a huge commitment we've
made sustainability is a priority for
our new ceo kevin strain has announced
that and announced a new chief
sustainability officer
um so i think you know it's certainly
something we're going to continue to
monitor and manage and look to do that
at the right opportunity
all right and helena
so so yeah we we are very
keen on on the green or sustainable
market you may know that manulife was
the first global life insurance company
that issued a green bond in 2017 in
singapore actually followed by the
second
global issue
of of the green bonds in canada in a in
a subject form uh we have like 40
billion dollars of undeniably green
assets on our balance sheet already uh
in terms of renewable energy uh we we
were involved in commercial solar and
wind farms since late 1990s because it
just made sense for for our long-term
business and and and returns
our real estate is over 80 green
certified etc and we are the largest
institutional um
timberland
manager uh with
managing 5.4 million acres of timberland
uh around the globe so so certainly and
we add to this portfolio in that like
sort of natural way one billion dollar
per year so certainly a lot of
opportunities for green or sustainable
financing we we also have investments in
education and social housing and similar
we have not issued since then since 2018
the green bond and why
i am very hesitant to issue anything
against uh maturity that's longer than
10 years the market is changing fast
changing regulations changing disclosure
requirements reputation risks
measurement etc so as such like going
longer than 10 uh years seems a bit sort
of extending this these risks too much
into the future and to to the elise
point yes we we did uh issue two billion
dollars of other cn in in february
uh 21
but because it's a 60-year non-call 5
instrument we didn't make it green and
similarly with our formosa bond i have
to say there was an interesting dynamic
earlier in the pandemic
we did issue in u.s senior debt that
would be more than suitable to to be in
a sustainable form but we refrained from
doing so based on the advice from the
banks at the time that there was so much
uncertainty and volatility in the
markets like measured by by hours almost
not not just days
that issuing in a green format back then
would create a one day a delay in terms
of marketing and explaining the
structure to to the investors and we
wouldn't benefit in terms of any break
on on on the issuance costs from from
this so so we didn't and i am just
amazed how much the market
changed since then
how many of insurance companies but also
other companies now uh have
sustainability frameworks in place and
and came to the markets with sustainable
or green financing so i'm quite sure
this advice would be very different uh
today even in in the uh uh
under the conditions of of high market
uh uncertainty i also have to say
because sometimes i'm asked like how
about
sustainability linked bonds and and
again like when i look at this whole
market the key risk in some ways is
reputation and measurement and
disclosure so
to me like the sustainability linked
bonds add to this risk in the sense that
now there is a kpi that the investors
and the issuer have to agree how to
measure if the investor is to get like a
better coupon after a certain time
period based on the the performance uh
against the commitments of the issuer or
not so to me it sort of adds to this
risk so for companies like this
reputation risk so for companies like
ours who have such big balance sheets
and and so many assets that that's
clearly a fall within the category of
sustainable
like just issuing in in that format uh
green formats sustainable format seems
like a a
a a good outcome uh
like to come to to take a stand on on
our support for the sustainability
agenda and at the same time to mitigate
those reputation and disclosure risks